Register of the Eugene H. Dooman Papers, 1918-1973.
Hoover Institution Archives
Eugene H. (Hoffman) Dooman Papers,
1918-1973
76052
Dooman, Eugene H., 1890-
2 manuscript boxes, 1 envelope (0.9 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Manuscripts of writings, transcripts of speeches, correspondence, diaries, and printed matter, relating to U.S. foreign policy in the Far East, U.S. Japanese relations, the decision to drop the atomic bomb on Japan, and Allied policy regarding the occupation of Japan.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1976.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
United States. Dept. of State.; United States. Embassy (Japan); Atomic bomb.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Diplomatic history.; World War, 1939-1945--Japan.; East Asia.; East Asia--Foreign relations--United States.; Japan.; Japan--Foreign relations--United States.; Japan--History--Allied occupation, 1945-1952.; United States--Foreign relations.; United States--Armed Forces.; United States--Foreign relations--East Asia.; United States--Foreign relations--Japan.; Diplomats--United States.; Nuclear energy.
Biographical Note
1890, March 25 Born, Osaka, Japan
1911 B.A., Trinity College
1912 Appointed student interpreter in Japan
1915 Vice-Consul, Kobe, Japan
1921 Assistant Japanese secretary, Tokyo
1924 Foreign Service officer
1926 Japanese Secretary and Second Secretary, Tokyo
1931 First Secretary, London
1936 Consul-General, London
1937-1941 Counsellor of Embassy, Tokyo
1942 Returned to State Department, Washington, D.C. American Minister and Charge d'Affaires, Moscow
1943 Returned to United States to help organize the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration (UNRRA)
1944 Appointed Special Assistant to Former Ambassador Joseph C. Grew Chairman of the Far East Sub-Committee of the State-War-Navy Coordinating Committee
1945 Advisor on Far East Affiars, Potsdam Conference
1944-1945 Advisor on Japanese affairs to Office of Strategic Services, Washington, D.C.
1969 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
Manuscripts of writings, transcripts of speeches, correspondence, diaries, and printed matter, relating to U.S. foreign policy in the Far East, U.S. Japanese relations, the decision to drop the atomic bomb on Japan, and Allied policy regarding the occupation of Japan.
Container List
- Correspondence, 1943-1965. (Box No. 1.)
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - Baldwin, Hanson W., 1964-1965 (Box 1.)
  - Feis, Herbert, 1949
  - Lilienthal, Philip E., 1948
  - Lilly, Edward P., 1947
  - Mandel, Benjamin, 1955-1957
  - Martin, Truman M., 1943-1944
  - Mitchell, Jonathan, 1956
- Speeches and Writings, 1931-1973. (Box No. 1.)
  Speeches, lectures, writings, and translation of a diary of a Japanese official, arranged alphabetically by title or subject.
  - "The A-Bomb and American Foreign Policy," speech to the St. Michael's Church Men's Club, January 12, 1960. 1 typewritten copy (Box 1.)
  - "Aggression in the Atomic Age." 1 carbon copy
  - "The American Council on Japan and Its Influence on Relations Between the United States and Japan," January 25, 1963
  - American foreign policy, speech notes
  - "Asia's Problems and Ours," speech to the Foreign Policy Association, November 5, 1945. Handwritten notes and newspaper clipping
  - "China and Japan," possibly written by Eugene H. Dooman. 1 typewritten copy.
  - "Diary of an Official of the Bakufu," translated for the Asiatic Society of Japan by Eugene H. Dooman, 1931. 6 printed copies
  - "How Long Will It Take to Defeat Japan?" speech at Walter Reed Hospital, May 23, 1945. 1 carbon copy
  - Japan. Lectures at Harvard to personnel in the military government preparing to go to Japan during the occupation, n.d.
  - Miscellaneous pages, speeches and/or writings, n.d.
  - "The Open Door and the Iron Curtain," (Part 1); "Bridges of Friendship," (Part 2); "Asia's Problems and Ours," (Part 3), n.d. 1 carbon copy of each part
  - Oral History Interview with Eugene H. Dooman for the Oral History Library, Columbia University, 1962. Includes 2 microfiche copies and typed and handwritten draft with comments, circa 1970s
  - "The Peace Treaty and "Democratization'," n.d. 1 typewritten copy
  - U.S. reply to Japanese surrender offer, n.d. Carbon draft with annotations
  - Speech to the American-Japan Society, Tokyo, September 26, 1952. 1 mimeographed copy
  - Speech to the American-Japan Society, Tokyo, October 11, 1961. 1 typewritten copy, 2 newspaper clippings
  - "Spiritual Evaluation Lacking Among Young Japanese," article by Eugene H. Dooman for The Mainichi Daily News, Tokyo, November 18, 1961. 1 newspaper clipping
  - "Tokyo: December 8, 1941," article in the Foreign Service Journal, December, 1966. 1 printed copy
  - "Whose State Department?" outline of lecture, n.d. 1 carbon copy
- Subject File, 1918-1966. (Box No. 2.)
  Articles, pamphlets, correspondence, and interviews, arranged alphabetically by title or subject.
  - Atomic bomb (Box 2.)
    - Correspondence, Joseph C. Grew and Henry L. Stimson, February, June, 1947; Joseph C. Grew and Eugene H. Dooman, April, May, 1948
    - Excerpts from letters, articles, book
    - Carbon copies of Joseph C. Grew's diary entries, May 28, May 29, 1945
    - Leighton, Alex H. "Atomic Bomb Wasn't Necessary," carbon copy of article which appeared in Science, April 20-26, 1947
    - Mumford, Lewis, "The Human Way Out," Pendle Hill Pamphlet, 1958
    - National Broadcasting Company (NBC). Correspondence 1964-1965, and interview, n.d., with Eugene H. Dooman
    - Stimson, Henry L., "The Decision to Use the Atomic Bomb," Harper's, February, 1947
    - Togo, Shigenori. Translation of Togo's Memoirs, April-August, 1945
  - Baldwin, Hanson W., "Our Worst Blunders in the War: Europe and the Russians," article, n.d.
  - Biographical material
  - Bulletin, International House of Japan, Inc., October, 1966
  - China
    - Communism
    - History - Yuan Dynasty, 1260-1368
  - Conference on British and American Policies Toward China, November, 1964.
  - Dooman, Isaac. Message of congratulations from the Governor of Nara Prefecture, Keigen Kitagawa, 1918 (in Japanese)
  - Emmerson, John K.
  - Grew, Joseph C.
  - Hornbeck, Stanley K.
  - "The Hull-Nomura Conversations: A Fundamental Misconception," reprint from the American Historical Review, July, 1960
  - Japan
    - Communism
    - History - Allied occupation, 1945-1952
    - Reports, trip reports by Eugene H. Dooman
  - Levine, Isaac Don, "Yalta Aftermath," American Affairs, July, 1945
  - Maine
  - Marshall, General George C. "Did Marshall Prolong the Pacific War?" by Forrest Davis, 3 reprints from the Freeman, November 19, 1951
  - Miscellaneous. Notes by Mrs. Eugene H. Dooman, newspaper clippings, unidentified typewritten pages, and handwritten outline.
  - Pearl Harbor. "The Truth about Pearl Harbor," by John T. Flynn, October, 1944
  - Perry, Commodore Matthew C., "Commodore Perry at Okinawa," by William Leonard Schwartz, reprinted from the American Historical Review, January, 1946
  - Potsdam. "Stalin Merely Smiled," by Charles Curran, The Spectator, September, 1959
  - United States
    - Department of State
    - Foreign Relations
      - General
      - Asia
      - China
      - Japan
    - Foreign Service
- Diary, December, 1941-June 16, 1942. (Box No. 2.)
- Audio-Visual., (1 print / 1 envelope (Box No. 2.)
  1 print of Eugene H. Dooman, Norman Davis, Admiral William Standley, Commander R.E. Schuirman and others (unidentified).